I'm going to go right into the slides.
سأذهب مباشرة لعرض الشرائح.
And all I'm going to try and prove to you with these slides
وكل الذي أريد أن أحاول اثباته لكم بهذه الشرائح
is that I do just very straight stuff.
أنني أقوم بأشياء مستقيمة فقط.
And my ideas are --
وأفكاري هي --
in my head, anyway -- they're very logical
في رأسي، على كل حال -- انها منطقية جدا
and relate to what's going on and problem solving for clients.
ومرتبطة بما يجري وحل المشاكل للزبائن.
I either convince clients at the end that I solve their problems,
أنا اما أن أقنع الزبائن في النهاية أنني حللت مشكلتهم،
or I really do solve their problems,
أو أكون بالفعل قد حللت مشكلتهم،
because usually they seem to like it.
لأنه بالعادة يبدو أنهم يحبون ذلك.
Let me go right into the slides.
دعوني أذهب مباشرة للشرائح.
Can you turn off the light? Down.
هل تستطيع اطفاء الأضواء؟ للأسفل.
I like to be in the dark.
أنا أحب أن أكون في العتمة.
I don't want you to see what I'm doing up here.
أنا لا أريد أن تروا ما أفعل هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, I did this house in Santa Monica,
على كل حال، لقد عملت هذا المنزل في سانتا مونيكا،
and it got a lot of notoriety.
وقد حصل على الكثير من سوء السمعة.
In fact, it appeared in a porno comic book,
في الواقع، لقد ظهر في مجلة اباحية،
which is the slide on the right.
الشريحة التي الى اليمين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is in Venice.
هذه في البندقية.
I just show it because I want you to know
أنا فقط أعرضها لأنني أريدكم أن تعرفوا
I'm concerned about context.
أنا مهتم بالنسيج.
On the left-hand side,
على جهة اليد اليسرى،
I had the context of those little houses,
كان لدي نسيج هذه البيوت الصغيرة،
and I tried to build a building that fit into that context.
وقد حاولت ان أبني بيتا يتوافق مع هذا النسيج.
When people take pictures of these buildings out of that context
عندما يلتقط الناس الصور لهذه المباني بعيدا عن هذا النسيج
they look really weird,
تبدو فعلا غريبة،
and my premise is that they make a lot more sense
و فرضيتي هي أنهم يعطوا معنى أكثر
when they're photographed or seen in that space.
عندما يلتقط لهم صورة أو يشاهدوا في ذلك النسيج.
And then, once I deal with the context,
وبعدها، عندما أتعامل مع النسيج،
I then try to make a place that's comfortable and private and fairly serene,
أنا أحاول ان أعمل مكانا مريحا وخاصا وهادئ نسبيا،
as I hope you'll find that slide on the right.
كما امل ان تجدوا تلك الشريحة الى اليمين.
And then I did a law school for Loyola in downtown L.A.
ومن ثم عملت كلية للقانون للويولا في وسط مدينة لوس انجيلوس.
I was concerned about making a place for the study of law.
لقد كنت مهتما بعمل مكان لتدريس القانون.
And we continue to work with this client.
وقد تابعنا العمل مع هذا الزبون.
The building on the right at the top is now under construction.
المبنى الذي الى اليمين في الأعلى الآن تحت الانشاء.
The garage on the right -- the gray structure -- will be torn down,
مصف السيارات الذي الى اليمين -- الانشاء الرمادي -- سوف يهدم،
finally, and several small classrooms will be placed
وأخيرا، و بعض الغرف الصفية الصغيرة سوف توضع
along this avenue that we've created, this campus.
على طول الجادّة التي أنشئناها، هذا حرم الجامعة.
And it all related to the clients and the students
وكلها ارتبطت بالزبائن والطلاب
from the very first meeting saying they felt denied a place.
من اللقاء الأول قالوا أنهم شعروا أنهم رفضوا المكان.
They wanted a sense of place.
لقد أرادوا حسا بالمكان.
And so the whole idea here was to create that kind of space
لذا كانت كل الفكرة هنا بعمل ذلك النوع من الفراغ
in downtown, in a neighborhood that was difficult to fit into.
في وسط المدينة، في حي كان من الصعب أن يندمج معه
And it was my theory, or my point of view,
وكانت نظريتي، أو وجهة نظري،
that one didn't upstage the neighborhood --
أن لا يعتلي الحي --
one made accommodations.
ان يعمل توافقات.
I tried to be inclusive, to include the buildings in the neighborhood,
حاولت أن أكون شموليا، بأن احتوي المباني في الحي،
whether they were buildings I liked or not.
سواء كانت مبان اعجبتني أم لا.
In the '60s I started working with paper furniture
في الستينات بدات العمل بالأثاث الورقي،
and made a bunch of stuff that was very successful in Bloomingdale's.
وعملت مجموعة من الأشياء التي كانت ناجحة جدا في بلومنغدايل.
We even made flooring, walls and everything, out of cardboard.
لقد عملنا حتى الارضيات، الجدران وكل شيئ، من ورق الكرتون.
And the success of it threw me for a loop.
ونجاحه قذف بي في دوامة.
I couldn't deal with the success of furniture --
لم أستطع التعامل مع نجاح الأثاث --
I wasn't secure enough as an architect --
لم أكن محميا كفاية كمعماري --
and so I closed it all up and made furniture that nobody would like.
لذا اغلقت كل شيئ وعملت أثاث لا يحبه أحد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, nobody would like this.
اذا، لا أحد سيحب هذا.
And it was in this, preliminary to these pieces of furniture,
وكانت في هذا، تمهيديا لهذه القطع من الأثاث،
that Ricky and I worked on furniture by the slice.
أني و ريكي عملنا على أثاث بالشرائح.
And after we failed, I just kept failing.
وبعد أن فشلنا، استمررت بالفشل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The piece on the left --
القطعة الى اليسار --
and that ultimately led to the piece on the right --
وهذه بالمطلق قادت الى القطعة على اليمين --
happened when the kid that was working on this
حصلت عندما كان الطفل الذي يعمل عليها
took one of those long strings of stuff and folded it up
أخذ واحدة من هذه العصي الطويلة من الأشياء وطواها
to put it in the wastebasket.
ليضعها في سلة المهملات.
And I put a piece of tape around it,
وانا وضعت شريط حولها،
as you see there, and realized you could sit on it,
كما ترون هناك، واستنتجت انه تستطيع أن تجلس عليها،
and it had a lot of resilience and strength and so on.
وكان لديها قدرة عالية على الانكماش والمتانة وما الى ذلك.
So, it was an accidental discovery.
لذا، لقد كان اكتشافا عرضيا.
I got into fish.
لقد اصطدت سمكة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, the story I tell is that I got mad at postmodernism -- at po-mo --
اعني، القصة التي أرويها أنني انزعجت من ما بعد الحداثة
and said that fish were 500 million years earlier than man,
وقلت أن السمك كان موجودا بـ 500 مليون سنة قبل الانسان،
and if you're going to go back, we might as well go back to the beginning.
واذا أردت أن تعود للوراء، ربما العودة للبداية.
And so I started making these funny things.
ولذا بدات بعمل هذه الأشياء المسلية.
And they started to have a life of their own and got bigger --
وبدأت تحصل على حياة خاصة بها وبدأت تكبر --
as the one glass at the Walker.
كالكأس الأولى في واكر.
And then, I sliced off the head and the tail and everything
وثم قطعت الرأس والذيل وكل شيئ،
and tried to translate what I was learning
وحاولت أن اترجم ما كنت أتعلمه
about the form of the fish and the movement.
عن شكل السمكة والحركة.
And a lot of my architectural ideas that came from it --
والكثير من أفكاري المعمارية أتت منها --
accidental, again --
صدفة، مرة أخرى--
it was an intuitive kind of thing, and I just kept going with it,
لقد كانت نوع من الحدس، وأنا استمرّيت بها،
and made this proposal for a building, which was only a proposal.
وعملت هذا المقترح للمبنى، الذي كان مجرد اقتراح.
I did this building in Japan.
عملت هذا المبنى في اليابان.
I was taken out to dinner after the contract
أُخذت للعشاء بعد توقيع العقد
for this little restaurant was signed.
لهذا المطعم الصغير.
And I love sake and Kobe and all that stuff.
وأحببت السايك والكوبي وكل تلك الأشياء.
And after I got -- I was really drunk --
وبعد أن تناولت -- كنت ثملا فعلا --
I was asked to do some sketches on napkins.
طلب مني رسم بعض الرسمات على المناديل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I made some sketches on napkins --
ورسمت بعض الرسومات على المناديل --
little boxes and Morandi-like things that I used to do.
مكعبات صغيرة وأشياء تشبه الموراندي اعتدت أن أعملها.
And the client said, "Why no fish?"
والزبون سأل، "لماذا لا يوجد سمك؟"
And so I made a drawing with a fish, and I left Japan.
لذا عملت بعض الرسومات مع سمك، وغادرت اليابان.
Three weeks later, I received a complete set of drawings
بعد ثلاثة أسابيع تلقيت مجموعة كاملة من الرسومات
saying we'd won the competition.
تقول أننا فزنا بالمسابقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, it's hard to do. It's hard to translate a fish form,
الآن، من الصعب عمل ذلك. من الصعب ترجمة السمكة الى شكل،
because they're so beautiful -- perfect --
لأنها جميلة جدا -- ممتازة --
into a building or object like this.
الى مبنى أو شيئ مثل هذا.
And Oldenburg, who I work with a little once in a while,
وأولدينبيرغ، الذي عملت معه مرة لفترة قصيرة،
told me I couldn't do it, and so that made it even more exciting.
قال لي أنني لا أستطيع عملها، وهذا جعل الأمر ممتعا أكثر.
But he was right -- I couldn't do the tail.
لكنه كان على حق -- لم أستطع عمل الذيل.
I started to get the head OK, but the tail I couldn't do.
بدأت بعمل الرأس حسنا، لكن الذيل لم أستطع انجازه.
It was pretty hard.
لقد كان صعبا جدا.
The thing on the right is a snake form, a ziggurat.
الشيئ الذي الى اليمين شكل أفعى، زقورة.
And I put them together, and you walk between them.
ووضعتهم معا، وتمشي بينهم.
It was a dialog with the context again.
لقد كان حوارا مع النسيج مرة أخرى.
Now, if you saw a picture of this
الآن، اذا رأيت صورة لهذا
as it was published in Architectural Record --
كما نشرت في أركيتيكشيرال ريكورد،
they didn't show the context, so you would think,
لم يظهروا النسيج، لذا ستعتقد،
"God, what a pushy guy this is."
"الهي، كم هذا الشخص متغطرس."
But a friend of mine spent four hours wandering around here
لكن صديقا لي أمضى أربع ساعات يحوم هنا
looking for this restaurant.
باحثا عن هذا المطعم.
Couldn't find it.
لم يستطع ايجاده.
So ...
لذا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As for craft and technology and all those things
كما في الحرف والتكنولوجيا وكل تلك الأشياء
that you've all been talking about, I was thrown for a complete loop.
التي كنتم تتحدثون عنها، لقد ارتميت في حلقة مغلقة.
This was built in six months.
تم بناء هذا في ستة أشهر.
The way we sent drawings to Japan:
الطريقة التي أرسلنا بها الرسومات الى الزبون --
we used the magic computer in Michigan that does carved models,
استعملنا حاسوب سحري في ميتشيغن يعمل نماذج منحوتة،
and we used to make foam models, which that thing scanned.
وقد اعتدنا أن نعمل نماذج من الفوم الذي يقرأه هذا الحاسوب.
We made the drawings of the fish and the scales.
عملنا رسومات السمك والمقاييس.
And when I got there, everything was perfect --
وعندما وصلت الى هناك، كل شيئ كان كاملا --
except the tail.
عدا الذيل.
So, I decided to cut off the head and the tail.
لذا، قررت قطع الرأس والذيل.
And I made the object on the left for my show at the Walker.
وعملت هذا المجسم الى اليسار لمعرضي في الواكر.
And it's one of the nicest pieces I've ever made, I think.
وهي واحدة من اجمل القطع التي صنعتها على الاطلاق، أعتقد.
And then Jay Chiat, a friend and client,
من ثم جاي شيات، صديق وزبون
asked me to do his headquarters building in L.A.
سألني عن عمل مبنى الادارة الرئيسي له في لوس أنجيلوس.
For reasons we don't want to talk about, it got delayed.
لأسباب لا نريد الحديث عنها، تم تأجيل الموضوع.
Toxic waste, I guess, is the key clue to that one.
النفايات السامة، كما أعتقد، هي مفتاح الحل لتلك.
And so we built a temporary building -- I'm getting good at temporary --
ولذا بنينا مبنى مؤقت -- أنا اصبح أفضل في المؤقت --
and we put a conference room in that's a fish.
ووضعنا غرفة مؤتمرات وتلك هي السمكة.
And, finally, Jay dragged me to my hometown, Toronto, Canada.
و في النهاية قادني جاي الى البلد التي نشأت فيها، تورنتو، كندا.
And there is a story -- it's a real story -- about my grandmother
وهناك قصة - انها قصة حقيقية -- عن جدتي
buying a carp on Thursday, bringing it home,
تشتري الشبوط يوم الخميس، وتأتي به الى المنزل،
putting it in the bathtub when I was a kid.
وضعته في حوض الاستحمام عندما كنت طفلا.
I played with it in the evening.
ولعبت به في المساء.
When I went to sleep, the next day it wasn't there.
عندما ذهبت الى النوم، في اليوم التالي لم يكن هناك.
And the next night, we had gefilte fish.
وفي الليلة التالية، اكلنا طبق كرات السمك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so I set up this interior for Jay's offices
لذا أنشأت هذا التصميم الداخلي لمكاتب جاي
and I made a pedestal for a sculpture.
وعملت قاعدة لتمثال.
And he didn't buy a sculpture, so I made one.
ولم يشتري تمثال، لذا عملت له واحدا.
I went around Toronto and found a bathtub like my grandmother's,
تجولت في تورنتو ووجدت حوض استحمام يشبه الذي لجدتي،
and I put the fish in.
ووضعت السمك فيه.
It was a joke.
هذه كانت نكتة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I play with funny people like [Claes] Oldenburg.
أنا ألعب مع أشخاص مسليين مثل أولدينبيرغ.
We've been friends for a long time.
لقد كنا أصدقاء لوقت طويل.
And we've started to work on things.
وبدأنا العمل على أشياء.
A few years ago, we did a performance piece in Venice, Italy,
قبل بضع سنوات، أدينا عملا في البندقية، ايطاليا،
called "Il Corso del Coltello" -- the Swiss Army knife.
اسمها" ال كورسو ديل كولتيللو" -- سكينة الجيش السويسري.
And most of the imagery is --
ومعظم الصور هي --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Claes', but those two little boys are my sons,
لكلايس، لكن هذان الولدان الصغيران هما ابناي،
and they were Claes' assistants in the play.
وكانوا مساعدين كلاي في المسرحية.
He was the Swiss Army knife.
لقد كان سكينة الجيش السويسري.
He was a souvenir salesman who always wanted to be a painter,
وكان بائع تذكارات يريد أن يصبح رساما،
and I was Frankie P. Toronto.
وأنا كنت فرانكي ب. تورنتو.
P for Palladio.
ب ل باللاديو.
Dressed up like the AT&amp;T building by Claes --
لابسا مثل مبنى أي تي أند تي لكلايس --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
with a fish hat.
مع قبعة سمكة.
The highlight of the performance was at the end.
التركيز في الأداء كان في النهاية.
This beautiful object, the Swiss Army knife,
هذا الشيء الجميل، السكينة السويسرية،
which I get credit for participating in.
التي أعطتني الامتياز للأداء بها.
And I can tell you -- it's totally an Oldenburg.
وأستطيع أن أقول لكم -- انها أولدينبيرغ بالكامل.
I had nothing to do with it.
لم يكن لدي شيء أفعله بها.
The only thing I did was, I made it possible for them
الشيء الوحيد الذي فعلته كان، جعلته ممكنا
to turn those blades so you could sail this thing in the canal,
بأن أحول هذه الشفرات كي تستطيع أن تبحر بها في القناة،
because I love sailing.
لأني أحب الابحار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We made it into a sailing craft.
جعلناها أداة ابحار.
I've been known to mess with things like chain link fencing.
لقد كنت معروفا بعبثي بوصلة سلسلة ربط السياج.
I do it because it's a curious thing in the culture,
أنا أفعلها لأنه شيء مثير في المجتمع
when things are made in such great quantities,
عندما تُصنع الأشياء بكميات كبيرة،
absorbed in such great quantities,
وممتصة بكميات كبيرة،
and there's so much denial about them.
وهناك رفض كبير لها.
People hate it.
الناس يكرهونها.
And I'm fascinated with that, which, like the paper furniture --
وأنا معجب بها، مثل الأثاث الورقي --
it's one of those materials.
انها واحدة من تلك المواد.
And I'm always drawn to that.
وأنا دائما غارق في ذلك.
And so I did a lot of dirty things with chain link,
ولذا عملت الكثير من الأشياء الوسخة بوصلة السلسلة
which nobody will forgive me for.
التي لن يسامحني أحد عليها.
But Claes made homage to it in the Loyola Law School.
ولكن كلايس عمل قبولا لها في جامعة لويولا للقانون.
And that chain link is really expensive.
وتلك وصلة السلسلة مكلفة حقا.
It's in perspective and everything.
انها في المنظور وكل شيء.
And then we did a camp together for children with cancer.
و عندما فتحنا معا معسكر من أجل الأطفال المصابين بالسرطان.
And you can see, we started making a building together.
ونستطيع أن نرى، بدأنا بعمل مبنى سوية.
Of course, the milk can is his.
بالطبع، علبة الحليب له.
But we were trying to collide our ideas,
لكننا حاولنا دمج أفكارنا معا،
to put objects next to each other.
لنضع الأشياء جنبا لجنب.
Like a Morandi -- like the little bottles -- composing them like a still life.
مثل موراندي -- مثل الزجاجات الصغيرة المشكلين كحياة ساكنة.
And it seemed to work as a way to put he and I together.
وبدت أنها تعمل كطريقة لوضعه هو وأنا معا.
Then Jay Chiat asked me to do this building
ثم طلب مني جاي شيات لعمل هذا المبنى
on this funny lot in Venice, and I started with this three-piece thing,
في هذه البقعة المسلية في البندقية، وبدأت بهذه الثلاث قطع،
and you entered in the middle.
و أنت تدخل من المنتصف.
And Jay asked me what I was going to do with the piece in the middle.
وسألني جاي ماذا سأفعل بهذه القطعة في المنتصف.
And he pushed that.
ودفعها.
And one day I had a -- oh, well, the other way.
و في يوم من الأيام أصابتني -- أوه حسنا، الجهة الأخرى.
I had the binoculars from Claes, and I put them there,
كان لدي الناظور من كلايس، ووضعتهم هناك،
and I could never get rid of them after that.
ولم أستطع التخلص منهم بعد ذلك.
Oldenburg made the binoculars incredible
أولدينبيرغ جعل الناظور رائعا
when he sent me the first model of the real proposal.
عندما أرسل لي النسخة الأولى من المجسم للمقترح الحقيقي.
It made my building look sick.
لقد جعلت مبناي يبدو مريضا.
And it was this interaction between
وكان هذا التفاعل بين
that kind of, up-the-ante stuff that became pretty interesting.
ذلك النوع من المادة المضادة التي أصبحت مثيرة جدا.
It led to the building on the left.
لقد قادت الى المبنى الذي على اليسار.
And I still think the Time magazine picture will be of the binoculars, you know,
وما زلت أعتقد أن صورة مجلة التايم ستكون للناظور ذو العينين، أنتم تعرفون،
leaving out the -- what the hell.
ترك الـ --(بحق الجحيم).
I use a lot of metal in my work,
أنا أستخدم الكثير من المعدن في عملي،
and I have a hard time connecting with the craft.
ولدي وقت عصيب بالتواصل مع الحرفيين.
The whole thing about my house,
كل الموضوع عن بيتي،
the whole use of rough carpentry and everything,
كل استخدام النجارة الخشنة وكل شيء،
was the frustration with the crafts available.
كان الاحباط من الحرفيين المتواجدين.
I said, "If I can't get the craft that I want,
وكما قلت، " اذا لم أتسطع أن أحضر الحرفي الذي أريد،
I'll use the craft I can get."
سأستخدم الحرفي الذي أستطيع احضاره.
There were plenty of models for that,
وكان هناك العديد من التجارب لذلك،
in Rauschenberg and Jasper Johns, and many artists
في روشينبيرغ وجاسبر جونز، والكثير من الفنانين
who were making beautiful art and sculpture with junk materials.
الذين كانوا يعملون فنا جميلا وتماثيل من مواد الخردة.
I went into the metal because it was a way of building a building
أنا ذهبت الى الحديد لأنها كانت طريقة لبناء مبنى
that was a sculpture.
بحيث يكون تمثالا.
And it was all of one material,
وكان كلّه من مادة واحدة،
and the metal could go on the roof as well as the walls.
والمعدن يستطيع أن يكون على السطح كما على الجدران.
The metalworkers, for the most part,
وعمال الحديد، في الجزء الأغلب،
do ducts behind the ceilings and stuff.
يضعون القنوات خلف الأسقف والأشياء.
I was given an opportunity to design an exhibit
أتيحت لي الفرصة لتصميم معرض
for the metalworkers' unions of America and Canada in Washington,
لاتحاد عمال الحديد الأمريكي والكندي في واشنطن،
and I did it on the condition that they become my partners
وعملته بظرف أنهم أصبحوا شركائي
in the future and help me with all future metal buildings, etc. etc.
في المستقبل وساعدوني في كل المباني الحديدية المستقبلية، الى آخره، الى آخره
And it's working very well
وانها تعمل بشكل ممتاز
to have these people, these craftsmen, interested in it.
بأن يكون لديك هؤلاء الناس، هؤلاء الحرفيين، مهتمين بها.
I just tell the stories.
أنا فقط أتلو القصص.
It's a way of connecting, at least, with some of those people
لقد كانت طريقة للتواصل، على الأقل، مع بعض هؤلاء الأشخاص
that are so important to the realization of architecture.
المهمين في استيعاب العمارة.
The metal continued into a building -- Herman Miller, in Sacramento.
استعمال الحديد استمر الى مبنى -- هيرمن ميلر، في ساكرامينتو.
And it's just a complex of factory buildings.
وانه فقط مجموعة من المباني الصناعية.
And Herman Miller has this philosophy of having a place --
وهيرمن ميلر لديه فلسفة بالحصول على مكان --
a people place.
مكان للناس.
I mean, it's kind of a trite thing to say,
أنا أقصد، انه شيء مبتذل للقول،
but it is real that they wanted to have a central place
لكنه حقيقي أنهم أرادوا مكانا مركزيا
where the cafeteria would be, where the people would come
حيث تكون صالة الطعام، حيث يستطيع الناس القدوم
and where the people working would interact.
و بحيث يتفاعل الناس العاملين.
So it's out in the middle of nowhere, and you approach it.
اذا انها في الخارج في وسط اللامكان، وأنت تقترب له.
It's copper and galvanize.
انه النحاس و الحديد المغلون.
I used the galvanize and copper
واستعملت المغلون والنحاس
in a very light gauge, so it would buckle.
بمعيار خفيف جدا بحيث يمكن أن يتشابك.
I spent a lot of time undoing Richard Meier's aesthetic.
اسغرقت وقتا طويلا بتفكيك جمالية ريتشارد ماير.
Everybody's trying to get the panels perfect,
الجميع يحاول أن بعمل صفائح ممتازة،
and I always try to get them sloppy and fuzzy.
وأنا دائما أحاول بأن أجعلهم مائلين وخشنين.
And they end up looking like stone.
وينتهون بأن يصبحوا مثل الحجر.
This is the central area.
هذه المنطقة المركزية.
There's a ramp.
هذا منحدر.
And that little dome in there is a building by Stanley Tigerman.
وتلك القبة الصغيرة مبنى من عمل ستانلى تايغرمان.
Stanley was instrumental in my getting this job.
ستانلي كان فعالا في حصولي على هذا العمل.
And when I was awarded the contract I, at the very beginning,
وعندما كوفئت بالعقد، في البداية الأولى،
asked the client if they would let Stanley do a cameo piece with me.
سألت الزبون اذا كان بامكانهم السماح لستانلي بعمل قطعة حجر كريم معي.
Because these were ideas that we were talking about,
لأنها كانت تلك هي الأفكار التي كنا نتحدث عنها،
building things next to each other, making --
بناء الأشياء بالقرب من بعضها البعض، عمل --
it's all about [a] metaphor for a city, maybe.
كل شيء هو عن استعارة للمدينة، ربما.
And so Stanley did the little dome thing.
لذا عمل ستانلي القبة الصغيرة.
And we did it over the phone and by fax.
وعملناها عن طريق الهاتف والفاكس.
He would send me a fax and show me something.
كان يرسل لي الفاكس، ويريني شيئا.
He'd made a building with a dome and he had a little tower.
لقد عمل مبنى بقبة وكان لديه برج صغير.
I told him, "No, no, that's too ongepotchket.
قلت له، " لا،لا، هذا عشوائي جدا.
I don't want the tower."
لا أريد البرج."
So he came back with a simpler building,
لذا عاد بمبنى أبسط،
but he put some funny details on it,
لكنه وضع بعض التفاصيل المضحكة عليه
and he moved it closer to my building.
وحركه قريبا من مبناي.
And so I decided to put him in a depression.
لذا قررت أن أحبطه.
I put him in a hole and made a kind of a hole that he sits in.
وضعته في ثقب وعملت ثقبا يجلس فيه.
And so then he put two bridges -- this all happened on the fax,
ولاحقا وضع جسرين -- هذا كله حصل على الفاكس،
going back and forth over a couple of weeks' period.
بالذهاب للوراء والأمام فترة عدة أسابيع.
And he put these two bridges with pink guardrails on it.
ووضع هذين الجسرين بحديد حماية زهري.
And so then I put this big billboard behind it.
لذا وضعت لوحة الاعلانات الكبيرة هذه خلفه.
And I call it, "David and Goliath."
وأسميتها،"داوود و طالوت."
And that's my cafeteria.
وهذه صالتي الطعام.
In Boston, we had that old building on the left.
في بوسطن كان لدينا هذا المبنى القديم الى اليسار.
It was a very prominent building off the freeway,
وكان مبنى بارزا جدا من الطريق السريع،
and we added a floor and cleaned it up and fixed it up
وأضفنا طابقا ونظفناه وأصلحناه
and used the kind of -- I thought -- the language of the neighborhood,
واستعملنا شيئا مثل -- أتذكر -- لغة الجيران،
which had these cornices, projecting cornices.
الذين كان لديهم هذه الكرانيش والزوايا المسقطة.
Mine got a little exuberant, but I used lead copper,
مبناي أصبح ضخما قليلا، لكنني استعملت النحاس الرصاصي.
which is a beautiful material, and it turns green in 100 years.
وهي مادة جميلة، وتصبح خضراء بعد 100 عام.
Instead of, like, copper in 10 or 15.
بدلا من، مثل، النحاس في 10 أو 15.
We redid the side of the building
أعدنا عمل جانب المبنى
and re-proportioned the windows so it sort of fit into the space.
وأعدنا عمل نسب الشبابيك كي تصبح ملائمة للفراغات.
And it surprised both Boston and myself that we got it approved,
وأدهشت كلانا بوسطن وأنا انها حصلت على الموافقة،
because they have very strict kind of design guideline,
لأن لديهم قيود على التصميم قاسية جدا،
and they wouldn't normally think I would fit them.
ولم يكونوا بفكرون بالعادة أنني أليق بهم.
The detailing was very careful with the lead copper
التفاصيل كانت دقيقة جدا بالنحاس الرصاصي
and making panels and fitting it tightly
وفي عمل الصفائح وضبطها باحكام
into the fabric of the existing building.
في نسيج المبنى القائم.
In Barcelona, on Las Ramblas for some film festival,
في برشلونة، في لاس رامبلاس لمهرجان أفلام.
I did the Hollywood sign going and coming,
عملت لافتة هوليوود تذهب وتأتي،
made a building out of it, and they built it.
عملت مبنى منها، وقاموا ببناءه.
I flew in one night and took this picture.
سافرت في ليلة واحدة واتقطت هذه الصورة.
But they made it a third smaller than my model without telling me.
لكنهم عملوه أصغر بثلث مجسّمي، بدون أن يخبروني.
And then more metal and some chain link in Santa Monica --
وثم المزيد من الحديد وبعض الشبه بالسلسلة في سانتا مونيكا --
a little shopping center.
مركز تسوّق صغير.
And this is a laser laboratory at the University of Iowa,
وهذا مختبر لليزر في جامعة أيوا،
in which the fish comes back as an abstraction in the back.
وفيه تعود السمكة للتجريد في الخلف.
It's the support labs, which, by some coincidence, required no windows.
انها مختبرات الدعم التي، بالصدفة، لم تحتاج الى شبابيك.
And the shape fit perfectly.
والشكل توافق تماما.
I just joined the points.
لقد وصلت النقاط للتو.
In the curved part there's all the mechanical equipment.
في الجزء الملتو توجد جميع المعدّات الميكانيكية.
That solid wall behind it is a pipe chase -- a pipe canyon --
وهذا الحائط الصلب خلفه متاهة أنابيب -- وادي من الأنابيب --
and so it was an opportunity that I seized,
لذا كانت فرصة لي حظيت بها،
because I didn't have to have any protruding ducts or vents or things in this form.
لأنه لم يكن علي أن أحصل على فتحات تهوية بارزة او أشياء في هذا الشكل.
It gave me an opportunity to make a sculpture out of it.
لقد أعطتني الفرصة لعمل منحوتة منها.
This is a small house somewhere.
هذا بيت صغير في مكان ما.
They've been building it so long I don't remember where it is.
لقد بنوه لمدة طويلة لدرجة أنني لا أتذكر اين هو.
It's in the West Valley.
انه في الوادي الغربي.
And we started with the stream
وبدانا مع التيار
and built the house along the stream -- dammed it up to make a lake.
وبنينا البيت على طول التيار -- طممناه لعمل بحيرة.
These are the models.
هذه هي المجسمات.
The reality, with the lake --
الحقيقية، في البحيرة --
the workmanship is pretty bad.
العمالة حقا سيئة.
And it reminded me why I play defensively in things like my house.
وذكرتني لماذا لعبت بطريقة دفاعية في اشياء مثل منزلي.
When you have to do something really cheaply,
عندما يكون عليك أن تفعل شيئا زهيدا حقا،
it's hard to get perfect corners and stuff.
من الصعب عمل زوايا كاملة وأشياء.
That big metal thing is a passage, and in it is --
ذلك الشيئ الحديدي الكبير هو ممر، وفيه --
you go downstairs into the living room and then down into the bedroom,
تذهب للأسفل الى غرفة المعيشة ومن ثم للاسفل لغرفة النوم،
which is on the right.
التي الى اليمين.
It's kind of like a whole built town.
انها مثل مدينة مبنية بالكامل.
I was asked to do a hospital for schizophrenic adolescents at Yale.
طُلب مني القيام بمستشفى للمراهقين المفصومين في جامعة يال.
I thought it was fitting for me to be doing that.
واعتقدت أنه يناسبني عمل هذا.
This is a house next to a Philip Johnson house in Minnesota.
هذا منزل بالجوار من منزل فيليب جونسون في مينيسوتا.
The owners had a dilemma -- they asked Philip to do it.
المالكين كان لديهم معضلة -- طلبوا من فيليب عملها.
He was too busy.
كان مشغولا جدا.
He didn't recommend me, by the way.
لم يوصي بي، بالمناسبة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We ended up having to make it a sculpture, because the dilemma was,
انتهينا بعملها تمثال، لأن المعضلة كانت،
how do you build a building that doesn't look like the language?
كيف تبني مبنى لا يشبه اللغة؟
Is it going to look like this beautiful estate is sub-divided?
هل ستبدو مثل هذا المبنى الجميل ؟ شبه مقسم؟
Etc. etc.
الى آخره، الى آخره.
You've got the idea.
لديك الفكرة.
And so we finally ended up making it.
واذا انتهى بنا الأمر بعمله.
These people are art collectors.
هؤلاء الناس جامعي تُحف.
And we finally made it so it appears very sculptural
وفي النهاية عملناه كي يبدو منحوتا جدا
from the main house and all the windows are on the other side.
من البيت الأصلي، وكل الشبابيك على الجهة الأخرى.
And the building is very sculptural as you walk around it.
والمبنى نحتي جدا وأنت تمشي حوله.
It's made of metal and the brown stuff is Fin-Ply --
انه مصنوع من الحديد والمادة البنية هي زعنفة رقيقة --
it's that formed lumber from Finland.
انها التي تشكل الخشب في فنلندا.
We used it at Loyola on the chapel, and it didn't work.
استعملناه في لويولا على المعبد، ولم ينجح.
I keep trying to make it work.
استمررت بجعلها تنجح.
In this case we learned how to detail it.
في هذه الحالة تعلمنا كيفية التعامل معها.
In Cleveland, there's Burnham Mall, on the left.
في كليفلاند، يوجد مجمع بيرنهام التجاري، الى اليسار.
It's never been finished.
لم يتم انهاءه أبدا.
Going out to the lake, you can see all those new buildings we built.
بالذهاب الى البحيرة، يمكنك مشاهدة كل تلك المباني التي بنيناها.
And we had the opportunity to build a building on this site.
و أتيحت لنا الفرصة لبناء منبنى في هذا الموقع.
There's a railroad track.
يوجد خط سكة حديد.
This is the city hall over here somewhere, and the courthouse.
هذه قاعة المدينة في مكان ما هنا، والمحكمة.
And the centerline of the mall goes out.
والخط المركزي للمبنى التجاري للخارج.
Burnham had designed a railroad station that was never built,
بيرنهام صمم محطة قطارات لم يتم تنفيذها,
and so we followed.
ثم تابعنا.
Sohio is on the axis here,
سوهيو على المحور هنا،
and we followed the axis, and they're two kind of goalposts.
وتبعنا المحور، وهناك نوعان من نقاط الأهداف.
And this is our building,
وهذا مبنانا،
which is a corporate headquarters for an insurance company.
وهو المقر الرئيسي لشركة تأمين.
We collaborated with Oldenburg and put the newspaper on top, folded.
لقد تعاونا مع أولدينبيرغ ووضعنا الصحيفة في الأعلى، مطوية.
The health club is fastened to the garage
النادي الصحي مثبت مع موقف السيارات
with a C-clamp, for Cleveland.
مع المشبك سي، لكليفلاند.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You drive down.
تقود نحو الأسفل.
So it's about a 10-story C-clamp.
اذن انه عبارة عن 17 طابق مشبك سي.
And all this stuff at the bottom is a museum,
كل هذه الأشياء في الأسفل هي متحف،
and an idea for a very fancy automobile entry.
وفكرة لدخول السيارات الفارهة.
This owner has a pet peeve about bad automobile entries.
هذا المالك لديه غيظ من دخول السيارات السيئة.
And this would be a hotel.
وهذا سيكون الفندق.
So, the centerline of this thing -- we'd preserve it,
اذا، خط المنتصف لهذا الشيء -- سنحتفظ به،
and it would start to work with the scale of the new buildings
و سيبدأ بالعمل مع مقياس المباني الجديدة
by Pelli and Kohn Pederson Fox, etc., that are underway.
لـ بيللي و كون بيديرسون فوكس، الى آخره، التي في الطريق.
It's hard to do high-rise.
انه من الصعب عمل ناطحات سحاب.
I feel much more comfortable down here.
أشعر بمزيد من الراحة في الأسفل هنا.
This is a piece of property in Brentwood.
هذه قطعة ملكية في برينت وود.
And a long time ago, about '82 or something, after my house --
و في وقت طويل مضى، حوالي 1982 أو شيء كهذا، بعد منزلي --
I designed a house for myself
أنا صممت منزلا لنفسي
that would be a village of several pavilions around a courtyard --
ليكون قرية من عدة أجنحة حول ساحة الدار --
and the owner of this lot worked for me
ومالكة هذه القطعة عملت لدي
and built that actual model on the left.
وبنت هذا المجسم الحقيقي الذي الى اليسار.
And she came back,
ثم عادت،
I guess wealthier or something -- something happened --
أعتقد أغنى أو شيء كهذا -- شيئ ما حدث --
and asked me to design a house for her on this site.
وسألتني أن أصمم لها منزلا في هذا الموقع.
And following that basic idea of the village,
وأتبع تلك الفكرة البسيطة للقرية،
we changed it as we got into it.
غيرناها عندما دخلنا فيها.
I locked the house into the site by cutting the back end --
أقفلت البيت الى الموقع عبر قطع النهاية الخلفية --
here you see on the photographs of the site --
هنا ترون الصور للموقع --
slicing into it and putting all the bathrooms and dressing rooms
قطعت فيه ووضعت جميع الحمامات وغرف الملابس
like a retaining wall, creating a lower level zone for the master bedroom,
كجدار استنادي، بصنع منطقة صغيرة أخفض لغرفة النوم الرئيسية،
which I designed like a kind of a barge,
التي صممتها كبارجة،
looking like a boat.
تبدو مثل زورق.
And that's it, built.
وهذه هي، مبنية.
The dome was a request from the client.
القبة كانت طلب من الزبونة.
She wanted a dome somewhere in the house.
أرادت قبة في مكان ما من المنزل
She didn't care where.
لم تهتم أين.
When you sleep in this bedroom, I hope --
عندما تنام في تلك الغرفة، أتمنى --
I mean, I haven't slept in it yet.
أعني، لم أنم فيها بعد.
I've offered to marry her so I could sleep there,
عرضت أن أتزوجها كي أستطيع النوم هناك،
but she said I didn't have to do that.
لكنها قالت أنه ليس علي فعل هذا.
But when you're in that room,
لكن عندما تكون في تلك الغرفة،
you feel like you're on a kind of barge on some kind of lake.
تشعر كأنك على بارجة في بحيرة ما.
And it's very private.
وهي خاصة جدا.
The landscape is being built around to create a private garden.
تنسيق الحديقة بني حول المنزل ليكوّن حديقة خاصة.
And then up above there's a garden on this side of the living room,
ثم في الأعلى يوجد حديقة على هذه الجهة من غرفة المعيشة،
and one on the other side.
وواحدة على الجهة الأخرى.
These aren't focused very well.
هؤلاء ليسوا مركّزين جيدا.
I don't know how to do it from here.
لا أعلم كيف أعملها من هنا.
Focus the one on the right.
ركز على التي في اليمين.
It's up there.
انها في الأعلى هناك.
Left -- it's my right.
يسار -- انه يميني أنا.
Anyway, you enter into a garden with a beautiful grove of trees.
على أي حال، تدخل الى حديقة مع شجر محفّر جميل.
That's the living room.
تلك غرفة المعيشة.
Servants' quarters.
مركز الخدم.
A guest bedroom, which has this dome with marble on it.
غرفة ضيوف، التي لديها هذه القبة مع الرخام عليها.
And then you enter into the living room and then so on.
ثم تدخل الى غرفة المعيشة وهكذا.
This is the bedroom.
هذه غرفة النوم.
You come down from this level along the stairway,
تأتي للأسفل من هذه الطبقة على سلم الدرج
and you enter the bedroom here, going into the lake.
وتدخل غرفة النوم هنا، ذاهبا الى البحيرة.
And the bed is back in this space,
والسرير في الخلف في هذا الفراغ،
with windows looking out onto the lake.
مع نوافذ مطلّة للخارج على البحيرة.
These Stonehenge things were designed to give foreground
هذه الحجارة صممت لتعطي مقدمة
and to create a greater depth in this shallow lot.
و تكوّن عمقا أكبر في هذه القطعة الضحلة.
The material is lead copper, like in the building in Boston.
المادة هي نحاس رصاصي، مثل المبنى الذي في بوسطن.
And so it was an intent to make this small piece of land --
لذا كانت النية لعمل قطعة صغيرة من الأرض --
it's 100 by 250 -- into a kind of an estate by separating these areas
انها 100 بـ 250 -- كقطعة عقار عبر فصل هذه المساحات
and making the living room and dining room into this pavilion
وعمل غرفة المعيشة وغرفة الطعام في هذا الجناح
with a high space in it.
مع فضاء عالى بها.
And this happened by accident that I got this right on axis
وهذا حصل بالمصادفة أنني حصلت على هذا الحق في المحور
with the dining room table.
مع طاولة غرفة الطعام.
It looks like I got a Baldessari painting for free.
بيدو أنني حصلت على لوحة بالديساري بالمجان.
But the idea is, the windows are all placed
لكن الفكرة هي، النوافذ كلها موضوعة
so you see pieces of the house outside.
كي ترى قطع من المنزل في الخارج.
Eventually this will be screened -- these trees will come up --
في النهاية هذا سيفحص -- هذه الشجر ستكبر للأعلى --
and it will be very private.
وسيكون خاصا جدا.
And you feel like you're in your own kind of village.
وستشعر كأنك في قريتك الخاصة.
This is for Michael Eisner -- Disney.
هذا لمايكل ايسنير -- ديزني.
We're doing some work for him.
نحن نقوم ببعض الأعمال له.
And this is in Anaheim, California, and it's a freeway building.
وهذا في أناهيم، كاليفورنيا، وهو مبنى على طريق سريع.
You go under this bridge at about 65 miles an hour,
تذهب تحت هذا الجسر بحوالي 65 ميلا في الساعة،
and there's another bridge here.
ويوجد جسر آخر هنا.
And you're through this room in a split second,
وأنت خلال هذه الغرفة في جزء من الثانية،
and the building will sort of reflect that.
والمبنى سيعكس شيئا من هذا.
On the backside, it's much more humane -- entrance,
في الجهة الخلفية، انه أكثر انسنانية -- المدخل،
dining hall, etc.
قاعة طعام، الى آخره.
And then this thing here -- I'm hoping as you drive by you'll hear
و ثم هذا الشئ هنا -- أنا آمل أنك وأنت تقود سوف تسمع
the picket fence effect of the sound hitting it.
أثرالصوت يضرب السور الوتدي.
Kind of a fun thing to do.
شيئ ممتع أن تقوم به.
I'm doing a building in Switzerland, Basel,
أنا أعمل مبنى في سويسرا، بازل،
which is an office building for a furniture company.
وهو مبنى مكاتب لشركة أثاث.
And we struggled with the image.
وكافحنا من أجل الصورة.
These are the early studies, but they have to sell furniture
هذه هي الدراسات الأولية، لكن عليهم أن يبيعوا أثاثا
to normal people, so if I did the building and it was too fancy,
لأشخاص عاديين، لذا اذا عملت المبنى وقد كان فاخرا جدا،
then people might say, "Well, the furniture looks OK in his thing,
قد يقول الناس، " حسنا، يبدو الأثاث جيدا في هذا الشيئ،
but no, it ain't going to look good in my normal building."
لكن لا، لن يبدو أنه جيد في مبناي الطبيعي."
So we've made a kind of pragmatic slab in the second phase here,
لذا عملنا بالطة واقعية في المرحلة الثانية هنا،
and we've taken the conference facilities and made a villa out of them
وأخذنا أدوات المؤتمر وعملنا منها فيلا
so that the communal space is very sculptural and separate.
حتى يكون المكان المشترك نحتيّ جدا ومفصول.
And you're looking at it from the offices and you create a kind of
وتنظر اليه من المكاتب وتخلق نوعا من
interaction between these pieces.
التداخل بين هذه القطع.
This is in Paris, along the Seine.
هذا في باريس، على طول نهر السين.
Palais des Sports, the Gare de Lyon over here.
قصر الرياضة، الـ "جاغي دي ليون " هنا.
The Minister of Finance -- the guy that moved from the Louvre -- goes in here.
وزارة المالية -- الشخص الي تحرك من اللوفر -- يأتي هنا.
There's a new library across the river.
يوجد مكتبة جديدة في الجهة المقابلة من النهر.
And back in here, in this already treed park,
وفي الخلف هنا، في هذه الحديقة المشجّرة سابقا،
we're doing a very dense building called the American Center,
نحن نعمل مبنى مكتظ جدا يدعى المركز الأمريكي،
which has a theater, apartments, dance school, an art museum,
وهو يحتوي على مسرح، شقق، مدرسة للرقص، متحف للفنون،
restaurants and all kinds of -- it's a very dense program --
مطاعم وجميع أنواع -- انه برنامج مكتظ جدا --
bookstores, etc.
المكتبات، الى آخره.
In a very tight, small --
في مكان ضيق جدا ، صغير --
this is the ground level.
هذا هو الطابق الأرضي.
And the French have this extraordinary way of screwing things up
والفرنسيين لديهم هذه الطريقة الخارقة لطي الأشياء
by taking a beautiful site and cutting the corner off.
عبر أخذ موقع جميل وقص الزاوية.
They call it the plan coupe.
يسمونه المخطط الكوبيه.
And I struggled with that thing --
وكافحت في هذا الشيء --
how to get around the corner.
كيف نأتي حول الزاوية.
These are the models for it.
هذه هي مجسماته.
I showed you the other model, the one --
أريتكم المجسم الآخر، الذي --
this is the way I organized myself so I could make the drawing --
هذه هي الطريقة التي نظمت بها نفسي حتى أعمل التصميم --
so I understood the problem.
لذا فهمت المشكلة.
I was trying to get around this plan coupe -- how do you do it?
كنت أحاول أن ألتف على هذا المخطط الكوبيه -- كيف تفعل هذا؟
Apartments, etc.
الشقق، الى آخره.
And these are the kind of study models we did.
وهذه هي مجسمات الدراسة التي عملناها.
And the one on the left is pretty awful.
والمجسم الذي الى اليسار بشع جدا.
You can see why I was ready to commit suicide when this one was built.
تستطيعون أن تنظروا لماذا قررت الانتحار عندما تم بنائه.
But out of it came finally this resolution, where the elevator piece
لكن خرج منه في النهاية هذا الحل، حيث قطعة المصعد
worked frontally to this, parallel to this street,
عملت بمواجهة هذه، بموازاة هذا الشارع،
and also parallel to here.
وأيضا بالموازاة هنا.
And then this kind of twist, with this balcony and the skirt,
وثم هذا الدوران، مع هذه الشرفة والجزء السفلي،
kind of like a ballerina lifting her skirt to let you into the foyer.
مثل لاعبة الباليه ترفع تنورتها لتدعني أمر الى البهو.
The restaurants here -- the apartments and the theater, etc.
المطاعم هنا -- الشقق والمسرح، الى آخره.
So it would all be built in stone, in French limestone,
لذا سيبنى كله بالحجر، بالحجر الكلسي الفرنسي،
except for this metal piece.
ما عدا هذه القطعة المعدنية.
And it faces into a park.
وتواجه المنتزه.
And the idea was to make this express the energy of this.
والفكرة كانت بجعل هذا يعبر عن طاقة هذا.
On the side facing the street it's much more normal,
في الجهة المواجهة للشارع انه أكثر اعتيادية،
except I slipped a few mansards down, so that coming on the point,
ما عدا أني زحلقت بعض السقوف للأسفل، لذا هذا يأتي الى النقطة،
these housing units made a gesture to the corner.
وحدات البيوت هذه تشير الى الزاوية.
And this will be some kind of high-tech billboard.
وهذا سيكون نوعا من لوح اعلانات عالي التقنية.
If any of you guys have any ideas for it, please contact me.
اذا كان لدى أي منكم أفكار لها، أرجوكم اتصلوا بي.
I don't know what to do.
لا أعلم ماذا أفعل.
Jay Chiat is a glutton for punishment, and he hired me
جاي شيات شره للعقاب، ووظفني
to do a house for him in the Hamptons.
لعمل منزل له في هامبتونز.
And it's got a fish.
ولديه سمكة.
And I keep thinking, "This is going to be the last fish."
وأنا أستمر بالتفكير، " هذه ستكون السمكة الأخيرة."
It's like a drug addict.
انها مثل الادمان على المخدرات.
I say, "I'm not going to do it anymore -- I don't want to do it anymore --
أنا أقول أني لن أعملها مرة أخرى -- أنا لا أريد أن أعملها مرة أخرى --
I'm not going to do it."
أنا لن أعملها.
And then I do it.
و من ثم أعملها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There it is.
ها هي.
But it's the living room.
لكنها غرفة المعيشة.
And this piece here is --
وهذه القطعة هنا هي --
I don't know what it is.
لا أعرف ما هي.
I just added it so that we'd have enough money in the budget
لقد أضفتها حتى يكون لدينا مال كاف في الميزانية
so we could take something out.
لذا يمكننا اخراج شيئا ما.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is Euro Disney, and I've worked with all of the guys
هذه ديزني أوروبا، وعملنا مع جميع الشباب
that presented to you earlier.
الذين عرضوا عليكم سابقا.
We've had a lot of fun working together.
استمتعنا كثيرا بالعمل معا.
I think I'm from Mars for them, and they are for me,
أنا أعتقد أني من المريخ بالنسبة لهم، وهم كذلك بالنسبة لي،
but somehow we all manage to work together,
لكن بطريقة ما قررنا جميعا العمل معا،
and I think, productively.
وأنا أعتقد، بانتاجية.
So far.
حتى الآن.
This is a shopping thing.
هذا شيء للتسوق.
You come into the Magic Kingdom
وأنت تأتي الى مملكة السحر
and the hotel that Tony Baxter's group is doing out here.
والفندق الذي تعمله مجموعة توني باكستر هنا --
And then this is a kind of a shopping mall,
وهذا مركز تسوق،
with a rodeo and restaurants.
مع روديو ومطاعم.
And another restaurant.
ومطعم آخر.
What I did -- because of the Paris skies being quite dull,
ما فعلته -- بسبب أن سماء باريس مملة،
I made a light grid that's perpendicular to the train station,
صنعت شبكة من الضوء متعامدة على محطة القطار،
to the route of the train.
لخط سير القطار.
It looks like it's kind of been there,
بدت كأنها هناك،
and then crashed all these simpler forms into it.
ثم سحقت كل هذه الأشكال البسيطة فيها.
The light grid will have a light, be lit up at night and give a
شكة الضوء ستحتوي على ضوء، تضاء في الليل و تعطي
kind of light ceiling.
سقف مضاء.
In Switzerland -- Germany, actually -- on the Rhine across from Basel,
في سويسرا -- ألمانيا، في الحقيقة -- على الراين بالمقابل من بازل،
we did a furniture factory and a furniture museum.
عملنا مصنع أثاث وتحف أثاث.
And I tried to -- there's a Nick Grimshaw building over here,
وحاولت أن -- هناك مبنى لغريم شو هنا،
there's an Oldenburg sculpture over here --
هناك منحوتة لألدينبيرغ هنا --
I tried to make a relationship urbanistically.
حاولت أن أعمل علاقة حضرية.
And I don't gave good slides to show -- it's just been completed --
وليس لدي شرائح جيدة لأعرضها -- لقد انتهي منه للتو --
but this piece here is this building, and these pieces here and here.
لكن القطعة هنا هي المبنى، وهذه القطع هنا وهنا.
And as you pass by it's always part -- you see it as all of these pieces
وعندما تمر بها دائما مفصولة -- تراها كان كل هذه القطع
accrue and become part of an overall neighborhood.
تتراكم وتصبح جزءا من حي كامل.
It's plaster and just zinc.
انها بلاستيك و زنك فقط.
And you wonder, if this is a museum,
وأنت تتسائل، اذا كان هذا متحفا،
what it's going to be like inside?
كيف سيبدو من الداخل؟
If it's going to be so busy and crazy that you wouldn't show anything,
اذا كان مشغولا جدا ومجنونا أن ترى شيئا،
and just wait.
وتنتظر فقط.
I'm so cunning and clever -- I made it quiet and wonderful.
أنا جدا بارع وذكي -- جعلته هادئا و رائعا.
But on the outside it does scream out at you a bit.
لكن في الخارج يصرخ عليك قليلا.
It's actually basically three square rooms
انه في الحقيقة ببساطة ثلاثة غرف مربعة
with a couple of skylights and stuff.
مع زوج من الفتحات السماوية وأشياء.
And from the building in the back, you see it as
ومن الجهة الخلفية للمبنى، تراه كأنه
an iceberg floating by in the hills.
جبل جليدي يطفو بين التلال.
I know I'm over time.
أنا أعرف أني تعديت الوقت.
See, that skylight goes down and becomes that one.
انظر، هذه الفتحة السماوية تنزل للأسفل لتصبح هذه.
So it's pretty quiet inside.
اذا انه هادئ جدا في الداخل.
This is the Disney Hall -- the concert hall.
هذه قاعة ديزني -- قاعة الحفلات.
It's a complicated project.
انه مشروع معقد.
It has a chamber hall.
فيه غرفة كبيرة.
It's related to an existing Chandler Pavilion that was built
انها مرتبطة بجناح تشاندلر الموجود الذي بني
with a lot of love and tears and caring.
بالكثير من الحب والدموع والاهتمام.
And it's not a great building, but I approached it optimistically,
وانه ليس مبنى عظيم، لكني توصلت اليه بتفاؤل،
that we would make a compositional relationship between us
أننا نستطيع عمل علاقة مركبة بيننا
that would strengthen both of us.
التي تقوينا كلا منا.
And the plan of this -- it's a concert hall.
ومخطط هذا -- انها قاعة حفلات.
This is the foyer, which is kind of a garden structure.
هذا هو البهو، الذي هو مثل بناء حديقة.
There's commercial at the ground floor.
هناك محلات تجارية في الطابق الأرضي.
These are offices, which, really, in the competition,
هذه مكاتب، التي، حقا، في المسابقة،
we didn't have to design.
لم يكن علينا تصميمها.
But finally, there's a hotel there.
لكن في النهاية، هناك فندق.
These were the kind of relationships made to the Chandler,
هذه كانت أنواع العلاقات مع تشاندلر،
composing these elevations together and relating them
تركيب هذه العلاقات معا وربطها
to the buildings that existed -- to MOCA, etc.
مع المباني الموجودة -- ل ام.أو.سي.أيه، الى آخره.
The acoustician in the competition gave us criteria,
مهندس الصوت في المسابقة أعطانا طريقة
which led to this compartmentalized scheme,
قادت الى هذا النمط المجزأ،
which we found out after the competition would not work at all.
الذي اكتشفناه بعد المسابقة أنه لن يعمل على الاطلاق.
But everybody liked these forms and liked the space,
لكن الجميع أعجبته هذه الأشكال و أعجبته الفراغات،
and so that's one of the problems of a competition.
واذا تلك واحدة من المشاكل لمسابقة.
You have to then try and get that back in some way.
اذن لقد حاولت و رجع عليك ذلك بطريقة ما.
And we studied many models.
ودرسنا العديد من النماذج.
This was our original model.
هذا كان نموذجنا الأصلي.
These were the three buildings that were the ideal --
هذه كانت المباني الثلاثة التي كانت مثالية --
the Concertgebouw, Boston and Berlin.
الكونسيرتجيبو، بوسطن وبرلين.
Everybody liked the surround.
الكل أعجبه المحيط.
Actually, this is the smallest hall in size,
في الحقيقة، هذه القاعة الأصغر حجما،
and it has more seats than any of these
وتحتوي مقاعد أكثر من أي من هؤلاء
because it has double balconies.
لأن لديها شرفتان مزدوجتان.
Our client doesn't want balconies, so --
زبوننا لم يرد شرفات، لذا --
and when we met our new acoustician, he told us
وعندما قابلنا مهندس الصوت الجديد، أخبرنا
this was the right shape or this was the right shape.
هذا كان الشكل الصحيح او هذا كان الشكل الصحيح.
And we tried many shapes, trying to get the energy
وجربنا العديد من الأشكال، محاولين الحصول على الطاقة
of the original design within an acoustical, acceptable format.
من التصميم الأصلي ضمن بنية صوتية مقبولة.
We finally settled on a shape that was
استقرينا في النهاية على شكل كان
the proportion of the Concertgebouw
نسب من كونسيرتجيبو
with the sloping outside walls, which the acoustician said
مع ميلان الجدران الخارجية، التي قال مهندس الصوت
were crucial to this and later decided they weren't,
أنها كانت متصالبة مع هذا ولاحقا قرر انها لم تكن،
but now we have them.
لكن الآن هم بحوزتنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And our idea is to make the seating carriage very sculptural
وفكرتنا كانت بعمل ناقل المقاعد نحتي جدا
and out of wood and like a big boat sitting in this plaster room.
ومن الخشب ومثل قارب كبير يجلس في هذه الغرفة الجبسية.
That's the idea.
هذه هي الفكرة.
And the corners would have skylights
والزوايا يكون لها فتحات للسماء
and these columns would be structural.
وهذه الأعمدة تكون تركيبية.
And the nice thing about introducing columns is they give you a
والشيء الجميل عن ادخال الأعمدة هو، أنها تعطيك
kind of sense of proscenium from wherever you sit,
نوع من الاحساس بخشبة المسرح من حيثما جلست،
and create intimacy.
وتخلق ألفة.
Now, this is not a final design -- these are just on the way to being --
الآن، هذا ليس تصميما نهائيا -- هذه على الطريق لكي تكون --
and so I wouldn't take it literally, except the feeling of the space.
ولذا لن آخذها بحرفية، ما عدا الاحساس بالفراغ.
We studied the acoustics with laser stuff,
درسنا الصوتيات بأجهزة ليزر،
and they bounce them off this and see where it all works.
وارتدت عن هذه ورأوا أين تعمل كلها.
But you get the sense of the hall in section.
لكنك تحصل على الاحساس بالقاعة في المقطع.
Most halls come straight down into a proscenium.
معظم القاعات تأتي للأسفل مباشرة الى خشبة المسرح.
In this case we're opening it back up
في هذه الحالة اننا نفتحها للأعلى
and getting skylights in the four corners.
ونحصل على الفتحات السماوية في الزوايا الأربعة.
And so it will be quite a different shape.
واذن سوف تصبح شكلا جديدا تماما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The original building, because it was frog-like,
المبنى الأصلي، لأنه كان شبيه الضفدع،
fit nicely on the site and cranked itself well.
تناسب بشكل جميل في الموقع ولوّى نفسه جيدا.
When you get into a box, it's harder to do it -- and here we are,
عندما تكون في صندوق، من الصعب عمله -- وها نحن هنا،
struggling with how to put the hotel in.
نعارك كيف نضع الفندق فيه.
And this is a teapot I designed for Alessi.
وهذا ابريق شاي صممته لـ أليسي.
I just stuck it on there.
لقد علقته هناك.
But this is how I do work. I do take pieces and bits and look at it
لكني أعمل هكذا. آخذ قطع و أجزاء وأنظر اليها
and struggle with it and cut it away.
وأتعارك معها وأقطعها بعيدا.
And of course it's not going to look like that,
وبالطبع لن تبدو مثل ذلك،
but it is the crazy way I tend to work.
لكنها الطريقة المجنونة التي أميل للعمل بها.
And then finally, in L.A. I was asked to do a sculpture
و في النهاية، في لوس أنجيلوس طلب مني عمل تمثال
at the foot of Interstate Bank Tower, the highest building in L.A.
على قدم برج بنك انترستايت، المبنى الأطول في لوس أنجيلوس.
Larry Halprin is doing the stairs.
لاري هالبرن يعمل الدرجات.
And I was asked to do a fish, and so I did a snake.
وسألت أن أعمل سمكة، وعملت أفعى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a public space, and I made it kind of a garden structure,
انه مكان عام، وعملته مثل حديقة تركيبية،
and you can go in it.
وبامكانك الدخول فيها.
It's a kiva, and Larry's putting some water in there,
انها كيفا، ولاري يضع بعض الماء فيه،
and it works much better than a fish.
وهي تعمل أفضل بكثير من سمكة.
In Barcelona I was asked to do a fish, and we're working on that,
في برشلونة طولبت بعمل سمكة، وكنا نعمل على ذلك،
at the foot of a Ritz-Carlton Tower being done by
في قدم برج ريتز-كارلتون الذي صنعه
Skidmore, Owings and Merrill.
سكيدمور، أوينجز و ميرل.
And the Ritz-Carlton Tower is being designed with exposed steel,
وبرج ريتز-كارلتون صمم بالفولاذ المكشوف،
non-fire proof, much like those old gas tanks.
غير مقاوم للحريق، يشبه كثيرا خزانات الغاز القديمة.
And so we took the language of this exposed steel and used it,
ولذا أخذنا لغة هذا الحديد المكشوف واستعملناها،
perverted it, into the form of the fish, and created a kind of
حورناها، لشكل سمكة، و صنعنا نوعا من
a 19th-century contraption that looks like, that will sit --
أداة غريبة الشكل للقرن التاسع عشر تبدو مثل، سوف تجلس --
this is the beach and the harbor out in front,
هذا هو الشاطئ والميناء في المقدمة،
and this is really a shopping center with department stores.
وهذا حقا مركز تسوق مع أقسام تخزين.
And we split these bridges.
و فصلنا هذه الجسور.
Originally, this was all solid with a hole in it.
بالأصل، هذا كله كان مصمت مع فتحة فيه.
We cut them loose and made several bridges and created a kind of
قصصناهم على نحو رخو و عملنا منهم عدة جسور وأوجدنا نوعا من
a foreground for this hotel.
مقدمة لهذا الفندق.
We showed this to the hotel people the other day,
عرضنا هذا على أصحاب الفندق في اليوم التالي
and they were terrified and said that nobody would come
وكانوا مرعوبين، وقالوا لن يأتي أحد
to the Ritz-Carlton anymore, because of this fish.
الى ريتز-كارلتون مرة أخرى، بسبب هذه السمكة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And finally, I just threw these in -- Lou Danziger.
و في النهاية، رميتها -- لو دانزيجر.
I didn't expect Lou Danziger to be here,
لم أتوقع أن يكون لو دانزيجر أن يكون هنا،
but this is a building I did for him in 1964, I think.
لكن هذا مبنى عملته له في 1964 كما أعتقد.
A little studio -- and it's sadly for sale.
استوديو صغير -- وللاسف انه للبيع.
Time goes on.
الزمن يمضي.
And this is my son working with me on a small fast-food thing.
وهذا ابني يعمل معي على محل وجبات سريعة صغير.
He designed the robot as the cashier, and the head moves,
لقد صمم الرجل الآلي كأمين الصندوق، والرأس يتحرك،
and I did the rest of it.
و أنا عملت الباقي.
And the food wasn't as good as the stuff, and so it failed.
والطعام لم يكن جيدا كما الأشياء، ولهذا فشل.
It should have been the other way around --
كان عليه أن يكون بالعكس --
the food should have been good first.
الطعام كان يجب أن يكون جيدا أولا.
It didn't work.
لم يعمل.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.